Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Moving Images Collection FILMS.001
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Moving Images Collection
1925-2005
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Transport Workers Union of America
FILMS.001
53 Linear Feet in 24 record cartons, 227 film cans, 1 cassette box, 1 manuscript box, 1 flat box, and 1 card box
630 film reels in 16mm film reels
17 film reels in 35mm film reels
4 film reels in 8mm film reels
3 film reels in super 8mm film reels
256 VHS
56 Betacam_SP
6 Digital_Betacam
8 Half_Inch_Video_Reel
3 MiniDV
1 U-matic
2 audiocassettes
2 DAT
8 DVDs
13.3 Gigabytes in 18 digital files
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Moving Images Collection contains film and video documenting organized labor and leftist movements in the United States from the 1930s-1970s, as well as recordings of Tamiment Library events in the 1980s-1990s. A majority of the collection is comprised of Transport Workers Union of America films and video reproductions, including elements and trims from documentary films and television programs, as well as recordings of conferences, press releases, mass meetings, negotiations, demonstrations, campaign speeches, and parades. This collection also includes programs and event recordings produced and distributed by several other labor and leftist organizations, including the American Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organizations Committee on Political Education (AFL-CIO COPE), the Jewish Labor Committee, the Socialist Party of the United States of America, the Communications Workers of America, the Seafarers International Union, and the United Steelworkers of America; works by filmmakers Louis W. Kellman and John Albok; documentaries from the mid-twentieth century about racial prejudice and political organizing; and video recordings of Tamiment Library events such as book receptions, conferences, memorials, and campus dedication ceremonies.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This is an assembled collection, and the provenance of the materials is varied. Materials were obtained through purchases, donations, arrangements with labor unions and other organizations, exchanges with other libraries, and internal transfers. Some materials were found in the repository, and may not have associated provenance documentation or accession records.
A majority of the materials in this collection were donated to the Tamiment Library by the Transport Workers Union of America in 1985. The accession number associated with this gift is 1950.223.
Film works by John Albok were donated by Ilona Albok Vitarius in 1993.
The film "Thirty-Fourth Anniversary Celebration for La Parola" was found in the repository and added to the collection. The accession number associated with this film is 2015.034.
The film May Day in New York City was donated by Jonathan Ned Katz in 2018. The accession number associated with this gift is 2018.090.
The film What's Happening in Harlem? was donated by Richard Frank.
The remaining materials were donated by various organizations and individual donors or separated from various Tamiment Library manuscript collections. The accession numbers associated with these materials are 2018.045, 2018.047, 2018.053, NPA.1993.024, NPA.1999.023, NPA.2000.055, NPA.2000.240, NPA.2000.343, NPA.2003.086, NPA 2004.013, NPA.2005.024, NPA.2005.180, NPA.2005.182, NPA.20015.195, NPA.2005.202, NPA.2005.204, NPA.2005.205, NPA.2005.206, NPA.2005.209, NPA.2005.212, NPA.2005.213, NPA.2005.216, and NPA.2006.099.
Appraisal
In 2023, 105 access DVDs were discarded after original videotapes were digitized. 12 VHS tapes and 17 DVDs were found to be commercial content and transferred to the Avery Fisher Center. Four U-matic tapes were transferred to the Deep Dish TV Records, MSS.312. In January 2025, 3 additional access DVDs were discarded.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into three series, one of which is further arranged in two sub-series:
Series I. Transport Workers Union of America Films
Sub-Series I.A. Films
Sub-Series I.B. Video Reproductions
Series II. Films on Organized Labor and the Political Left
Series III: Tamiment Library Event Recordings.
Each series is arranged chronologically except for Sub-Series I.B., which is arranged alphabetically.
Historical Note
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Moving Images Collection contains film and video documenting organized labor and leftist movements in the United States from the 1930s-1970s, as well as recordings of Tamiment Library events in the 1980s-1990s.
The majority of the collection is film and video recordings that document the Transport Workers Union of America's activities between 1930-1970. The Transport Workers Union of America (TWU) was founded in New York City in 1934 by subway workers. Michael J. Quill (1905-1966), a Kerry native and subway ticket clerk, led early organizing efforts for the TWU and became its first president. It soon became the bargaining agent for all New York City bus and subway systems, and branched out to form locals across the country. By the early 1950s, the Union's membership had grown to over 100,000, in both public and privately-owned transit lines. By the 1960s, TWU locals were also established among railroad, airlines, and utility workers and taxi drivers. From its early days, the TWU made use of radio, film, and television to communicate with its members as well as the general public. Most of the Union's programs were made by professional filmmakers and producers, including Paul Miner, Tom Costigan, and Leo Seltzer.
This collection also contains works by several other labor and leftist organizations. The Jewish Labor Committee, an umbrella group of Jewish or Jewish-led trade unions and fraternal organizations, was founded in New York City in 1934. Its primary purposes were to organize anti-Nazi and anti-fascist activity and to provide assistance to European Jews and others persecuted by these movements. During World War II, it maintained close ties with European resistance movements and was able to effect the rescue of hundreds of labor and socialist activists and their families. After the War, it assisted and resettled survivors and helped to reunite families, and became active in civil rights and labor rights campaigns in the United States and human rights work world wide.
The American Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO) is the largest federation of unions in the United States, made up of 60 unions and representing more than 12 million workers. It was formed in 1955 when AFL and CIO merged. The federation's Committee on Political Education (COPE) was established shortly after the merger in 1955, itself a combination of the CIO's Political Action Committee and AFL's Labor League for Political Education. COPE activities have included political research, grassroots voter mobilization efforts, candidate endorsements, and advocacy for issues affecting workers' rights. COPE is now decentralized and local chapters are active across the country.
This collection also includes works by individual filmmakers who documented labor and leftist history in the United States. John Albok (1894-1982) was a still photographer and filmmaker known for his depiction of New York City street life from the Depression through the 1960s, as well as trade-union and leftwing political protest and culture during this same period. Louis W. Kellman's film Tales From Tamiment depicts Camp Tamiment, a summer resort for socialists near Bushkill, Pennsylvania, that opened in 1921. Initially tied to the Rand School of Social Science, it also later became home to the Tamiment Playhouse.
Sources:
Albok, John. John Albok: For the Children. Dallas, Texas: Photographic Archives Gallery, 1995.
Huberman, Leo. The Great Bus Strike. New York: Modern Age Books, 1941.
Freeman, Joshua. In Transit (New York, Oxford University Press, 1989).
John Albok, 1894-1982: Through the Eye of the Needle. Budapest: Hungarian Multicultural Center, Inc., 1998.
LoMonaco, Martha. Every Week, a Broadway Revue: The Tamiment Playhouse, 1921-1960. New York: Greenwood Press, 1992.
Malmgreen, Gail. "Labor and the Holocaust: The Jewish Labor Committee and the Anti-Nazi Struggle." Labor's Heritage, Vol. 3, no. 4 (October 1991).
Quill, Shirley. Mike Quill Himself: A Memoir. Greenwich, CT: Devin-Adair Publishers, 1985.
University of Maryland Libraries. "Committee on Political Education." Curated by Laura Cleary and Amber Kohl. https://exhibitions.lib.umd.edu/get-out-the-vote/cope. Accessed December 7, 2023.
Whittemore, L. H. The Man Who Ran the Subways: The Story of Mike Quill. New York: Holt, Rinehart and Winston, 1968.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to some audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room.
Some audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu, (212) 998-2630 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Related Materials
The following collections in the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives are related to FILMS.001 materials:
Transport Workers Union of America Records (WAG.235)
Transport Workers Union of America, Records of Locals (WAG.234)
Jewish Labor Committee Records (WAG.025.001, WAG.025.002, WAG.025.003)
Communications Workers of America Records (WAG.124)
Communications Workers of America Film Collection (FILMS.004)
National Maritime Union and SIU Reference Files (WAG.267)
New York State AFL-CIO Records (WAG.031)
International Alliance of Theatrical Stage Employees, Local 52 Records (WAG.251)
Retail, Wholesale, and Department Store Union (RWDSU), Local 1-S, Records (WAG.012)
Retail, Wholesale, and Department Store Union (RWDSU), Local 3, United Store Workers Records (WAG.230).
Scope and Contents
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Moving Images Collection contains film and video documenting organized labor and leftist movements in the United States, as well as recordings of Tamiment Library events in the 1980s-1990s.
Series I. Transport Workers Union of America Films (1930-1977) includes original films and video transfers of the Transport Workers Union of America's activities between 1930 and 1970, which make up a majority of the collection. These films include prints, elements, and trims from the films United We are Invincible (1941), Our Case for the Forty-Hour Work Week (1950), Memorial Tribute to Mr. CIO – Allan S. Haywood (1953), Twenty-Nine Days to Victory (1953), Years of Challenge (1961), and The Best is Yet to Come (1967). Other Transport Workers Union films contain footage of conferences, press releases, mass meetings, negotiations, demonstrations, campaign speeches, and parades. Materials in this series focus mostly on the activities of Local 100 (New York City bus and subway workers), Local 101 (Brooklyn Union Gas utility workers), and Local 234 (Philadelphia transit workers). TWU figures frequently represented in these materials include Union President Michael Quill, Union President Matthew Guinan, Union Vice President Frank Sheehan, CIO Director Allan Haywood, and Local 100 President Ellis Van Riper. Former New York City Mayor Robert F. Wagner Jr. is also depicted giving campaign speeches to the Union.
Series II. Films on Organized Labor and the Political Left (1925-2005) includes programs and event recordings produced and distributed by labor and leftist organizations, mainly on the topics of socialism, communism, civil rights, and labor organizing. Organizations represented in this series include the American Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organizations Committee on Political Education (AFL-CIO COPE), the Jewish Labor Committee, the Socialist Party, the United Auto Workers, the Communications Workers of America, the Seafarers International Union, the International Alliance of Theatrical Stage Employees, the Retail, Wholesale and Department Store Union, the United Steelworkers Union, the American Postal Workers Union, United Voice, and United Financial Employees. This series also includes works by individual filmmakers, such as Louis W. Kellman's Tales From Tamiment about Camp Tamiment, John Albok's footage of New York City during the Great Depression, and recordings of New York City parades in the early twentieth century. Together with the TWU materials in Series I., these films provide insight into the history of labor and leftist movements in the U.S., as well as a candid portrayal of New York City life during the 1930s-1960s.
Series III. Tamiment Library Event Recordings (1979-2003) contains videos of events organized by Tamiment Library, which celebrated figures and explored topics related to the film subjects in Series I. and II. These events include receptions for written publications by authors including Ron Jacobs, Zellig Harris, Paul LeBlanc, Frank Lovell, Scott McLemee, Alan Wald, JoAnn Wypijewski, and Jeremy Brecher; symposiums and discussions on the topics of poverty during the Clinton administration, being openly gay at work, academic labor, Trotskyism in the United States, and the Spanish Civil War, among others; and memorials for Phil Foner, Frank Lovell, Myra Tanner Weiss, and Cedric Belfrage. This series also includes flyers for the recorded events, and one poster for "Between Classes: A Conference on Academic Labor."
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted.
An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Motion pictures (visual works); Documentary films; Transport workers -- New York (N.Y.); Strikes and lockouts.; Strikes and lockouts -- Public utilities -- New York (State) -- New York.; Subways -- Maintenance and repair.; Subways -- New York (State) -- New York.; Consolidation and merger of corporations.; Labor contract.; Bus drivers.; Negotiations.; Labor union meetings.; Labor unions; Airlines -- Employees -- Labor unions; Iron and steel workers -- Labor unions -- United States.; Civil rights and socialism -- United States; Labor unions and socialism -- United States.; Communism and motion pictures -- United States.; Jewish Labor Committee (U.S.); AFL-CIO. New York City Central Labor Council; Horst, James R.; Kellman, Louis; Miner, Paul; Debs, Eugene V. (Eugene Victor), 1855-1926; Haywood, Allan S., 1888-1953; Congress of Industrial Organizations (U.S.); Sheehan, Frank; Van Arsdale, Harry, 1905-1986; Van Riper, Ellis.; Quill, Mike, 1905-1966; New York City CIO Council; International Labour Organisation; Transport Workers Union of America. Local 100; Transport Workers Union of America. Local 234 (Philadelphia, Pa.); Pennsylvania Railroad; Costigan, Tom; Guinan, Matthew K.; Seafarers International Union of North America; United Steelworkers of America; United Automobile, Aircraft, and Vehicle Workers of America. District 65; Communications Workers of America
- Series I. Transport Workers Union of America Films, 1930-1977; 34.5 Linear Feet in 16 record cartons and 177 film cans; 13.3 Gigabytes in 18 digital files
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. Transport Workers Union of America Films (1930-1977) includes original films and video transfers of the Transport Workers Union of America's activities between 1930 and 1970, which make up a majority of the collection. The films in Subseries I.A. include prints, elements, and trims from the films United We are Invincible (1941), Our Case for the Forty-Hour Work Week (1950), Memorial Tribute to Mr. CIO – Allan S. Haywood (1953), Twenty-Nine Days to Victory (1953), Years of Challenge (1961), and The Best is Yet to Come (1967). Other Transport Workers Union films in Subseries I.A. contain footage of conferences, press releases, mass meetings, negotiations, demonstrations, campaign speeches, and parades. Video reproductions in Subseries I.B. are compilations containing transfers and excerpts of the films in Subseries I.A.
  Materials in this series focus mostly on the activities of Local 100 (New York City bus and subway workers), Local 101 (Brooklyn Union Gas utility workers), and Local 234 (Philadelphia transit workers). TWU figures frequently represented in these materials include Union President Michael Quill, Union President Matthew Guinan, Union Vice President Frank Sheehan, CIO Director Allan Haywood, and Local 100 President Ellis Van Riper. Former New York City Mayor Robert F. Wagner Jr. is also depicted giving campaign speeches to the Union.
  Historical Note
  The Transport Workers Union of America (TWU) was founded in New York City in 1934 by subway workers. It soon became the bargaining agent for all New York City bus and subway systems, and branched out to form locals across the country. By the early 1950s, the Union's membership had grown to over 100,000 and included members from both public and privately-owned transit lines. By the 1960s, TWU locals were also established among railroad, airlines, utility workers, and taxi drivers. The TWU actively supported equal rights for Black Americans. In the decade following World War II, it fought for a five-day, forty-hour week for its members.
  Many of the TWU's founders were Irish immigrants who came to the United States after the Easter Rising of 1916. Among them was Michael J. Quill (1905-1966), a Kerry native and subway ticket clerk who led early organizing efforts for the TWU and became its first president. He was elected to two terms on New York's City Council, was the chairman of the City's CIO Council, and later served as a vice president on the AFL-CIO's executive council.
  From its early days, the TWU made use of radio and moving images to communicate with its members and the general public. It recorded important meetings, produced hundreds of radio advertisements, filmed Union soapbox speakers and rallies, and documented TWU field days and victory rallies during World War II. In 1941, the Union produced its first film, United We Are Invincible, which told the story of the union's strike against New York City bus lines. This was followed by several other films commissioned by the Union. The TWU also embraced the new medium of television in early 1951, when it launched its first television program. Most of the Union's programs were made by professional filmmakers and producers, including Paul Miner, Tom Costigan, and Leo Seltzer.
  - Subseries I.A. Films, 1930-1977
    Arrangement
    This subseries is arranged chronologically, with film elements from the same production or event grouped together.
    - Demonstration and Rally, circa 1930s (Film canister c1, 16mm film reels 001_0799)
      Existence and Location of Copies
      See the video reproduction cuid36982 in Subseries I.B.
      Early demonstration by Transport Workers Union; early footage of some of the Union's founding member leaders speaking at a rally.
    - Rally at City Hall, circa 1930s (Film canister c1, 16mm film reels 001_0803)
    - Transit and Election Footage, circa 1930s (Film canister c1, 16mm film reels 001_0800)
      Exterior of bus company garage; 1930s street scenes in New York City boroughs; Transport Workers Union elections.
    - Transport Hall, Negotiations with Mayor, circa 1930s-1940s (Film canister c1, 16mm film reels 001_0802)
      Transport Workers Union bus drivers; Transport Workers Union's Transport Hall; Philip Murray negotiates with New York City mayor.
    - The Tom Mooney Case, 1936 (Film canister c125, 16mm film reels 001_0257)
      Tom Mooney reads from a written statement, on camera and in voiceover, recalling his personal history and the labor history of the time as context for the story of his arrest, trial, and imprisonment. It is intercut occasionally with stock footage and stills.
    - International Workers Order Picnic, May Day Parade, May, 1937 (Film canister c104, 16mm film reels 001_0278)
      See the video reproduction cuid1032 in Subseries I.B.
      International Workers Order (IWO) picnic; May Day parade, Union Square, New York City.
    - Historical Clips, 1939-1945 (Film canister c198A-2, 16mm film reels 001_0768)
      See the video reproduction cuid37016 in Subseries I.B.
      Films spliced together for transferral to videos. Includes: 1939 Quill Re-election;1939 Local 100 election; 1939 city hall demonstration;1941 Convention; 1941 United We Are Invincible; 1942 "Defend America"; 1942 NY at war; 1945 Field Day; circa 1940s Field Day; circa 1940s hearing; circa 1940s American Airlines.
    - Picket Line, circa 1940 (Box 16, Film canister c4, 16mm film reels 001_0386)
      See the video reproduction cuid1024 in Subseries I.B.
      Transport Workers Union strikers' picket line. Transport Workers Union pickets home of individual ex-member.
    - Demonstration, circa 1940-1941 (Box 16, Film canister c4, 16mm film reels 001_0385)
      Transport Workers Union members picket the homes of more than a dozen individual TWU members (different Manhattan locations and other boroughs) who have "deserted" the union; Michael Quill and other union leaders are shown speaking at outdoor rallies.
    - Demonstration, circa 1940s (Film canister c116, 16mm film reels 001_0341)
      Transport Workers Union demonstration in three locations (possibly New York City's outer boroughs or Washington Heights). Picket signs include the following slogans: "We Want Our Lunch Break Back," "We Want Retroactive Pay," "Don't Want 9 1/2 Hour Day," "United/Invincible."
    - Historical Clips, circa 1940s (Film canister c239, 16mm film reels 001_0790)
      Several different sequences on one roll, including Rally for Michael Quill's re-election to the New York City council (1939); Speakers at ca. 1940's union meeting indoors (Possibly 1939 Local 100 election campaign); TWU convention delegates ca. 1940's; Third Biennial TWU Convention; 1939 City Hall demonstration; "Defend America" pro-WWII rally and parade, 1942; Field Day, ca. 1940s; "11th Annual Outing and Dance," ca. 1945; Man testifying at a hearing.
    - Philip Murray Memorial Compilation, circa 1940s - 1950s (Film canister c156, 16mm film reels 001_0206)
      Includes silent footage of Philip Murray addressing a convention or a meeting; Murray announcing agreement over a TWU contract after a meeting with New York City Mayor O'Dwyer (probably 1949); Murray speaking out against Communism and supporting United States efforts against it. Some of this footage is probably from the commercial stock footage house Movietone News.
    - Bus Strike, circa 1940s-1950s (Box 16, Film canister c140, 16mm film reels 001_0391)
      Two Transport Workers Union meetings.
    - Picket Line, circa March, 1941 (Film canister c235, 16mm film reels 001_0032)
    - Bus Drivers Occupational Maladies Strike Meeting, circa 1941 (Film canister c6, 16mm film reels 001_0891)
      A discussion of bus drivers' occupational maladies; a Transport Workers Union strike meeting.